Guide to the James Andrew Riddick papers, 1834-1903
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
James Andrew Riddick papers 1834-1903
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Riddick, James Andrew, 1810-1899
1.3 Linear Feet 620 Items
James Andrew Riddick, born September 13, 1810, near Sunsbury, N.C., died 1899, Petersburg, Va. As a youth, moved to Suffolk, Va., to become a clerk in his brother-in-law's mercantile establishment. Became a Methodist minister in the 1830s and served in this capacity in North Carolina, Virginia, and Tennessee.
The James Andrew Riddick papers includes mostly sermons and other writings by Methodist Reverend James Andrew Riddick. The majority of the sermons are undated and titled with only a book, chapter, and verse. However, some sermons are dated (1834-1844) and include title information with the location the sermon was given. These locations include Charlotte, Edenton, and Elizabeth City, North Carolina and Charlottesville, Richmond, and Randolph-Macon College, Ashland, Virginia. Other miscellaneous writings and notebooks date 1835-1886. There are also newspapers dated 1863-1903 with articles or letters to the editor written by or about Riddick, or collected by Riddick. Additionally, there is correspondence received by Riddick dated 1854-1899. The bulk of the correspondence is from John Early who Riddick worked with early in his career. There are photographs of Riddick as well as photographs of his daughters Judith, Lucie, and Bettie. Also included in this collection are papers with biographical information about Riddick and his letters of reference dated 1835-1899, a few miscellaneous financial papers dated 1830-1899, and a few miscellaneous printed materials collected by Riddick.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Andrew Riddick papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Biographical Note
James Andrew Riddick, born September 13, 1810, near Sunsbury, N.C., died 1899, Petersburg, Va. As a youth, moved to Suffolk, Va. to become a clerk in his brother-in-law's mercantile establishment. Became a Methodist minister in the 1830s and served in this capacity in North Carolina, Virginia, and Tennessee.
Collection Overview
The James Andrew Riddick papers includes mostly sermons and other writings by Methodist Reverend James Andrew Riddick. The majority of the sermons are undated and titled with only a book, chapter, and verse. However, some sermons are dated (1834-1844) and include title information with the location the sermon was given. These locations include Charlotte, Edenton, and Elizabeth City, North Carolina and Charlottesville, Richmond, and Randolph-Macon College, Ashland, Virginia. Other miscellaneous writings and notebooks date 1835-1886. There are also newspapers dated 1863-1903 with articles or letters to the editor written by or about Riddick, or collected by Riddick. Additionally, there is correspondence received by Riddick dated 1854-1899. The bulk of the correspondence is from John Early who Riddick worked with early in his career. There are photographs of Riddick as well as photographs of his daughters Judith, Lucie, and Bettie. Also included in this collection are papers with biographical information about Riddick and his letters of reference dated 1835-1899, a few miscellaneous financial papers dated 1830-1899, and a few miscellaneous printed materials collected by Riddick.
Sermons are organized in folders grouped alphabetically by bible book and arranged within each folder numerically by chapter and verse. Sermons that do not refer to any book are grouped in a miscellaneous sermons and writings folder. Correspondence from John Early has been foldered separately from all other general correspondence and arranged by date. Newspapers have been arranged in folders by title and within each folder by date. Box 3 is oversize.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Riddick, James Andrew, 1810-1899
Early, John, 1786-1873
Methodist Episcopal Church, South
Methodist Church -- Clergy
Methodist Church -- History
Methodist Church -- Sermons
Methodist preaching
Religion
United States -- Religion -- 19th century
North Carolina
Virginia
Tennessee
Sermons
Card photographs (photographs).
Newspapers
Contents of Collection
- James Andrew Riddick papers, 1834-1903, (3 boxes)
  - Sermons: Acts, 1838-1840 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Amos, 1835 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Chronicles, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Corinthians, 1835-1840 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Daniel, 1839 (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Deuteronomy, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Ecclesiastes, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Ephesians, 1835-1839 (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Exodus, 1834 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Ezekiel, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Genesis, 1837-1841 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Hebrews, 1835-1840 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Hosea, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Isaiah, 1837-1838 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: James, 1835 (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Jeremiah, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Job, 1834 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: John, 1835-1841 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Jonah, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Joshua, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Jude, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Kings, 1835 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Luke, 1836-1838 and undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons: Malachi, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Mark, 1835 and undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Matthew, 1837-1841 and undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Numbers, 1835 and undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Peter, 1844 and undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Philippians, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Proverbs, 1835-1840 (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Psalms, 1835-1841 and undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Revelations, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Romans, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Samuel, 1836 (Box 2)
  - Sermons: Timothy, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous sermons and writings, 1835-1843 and undated (Box 2)
  - Notebooks, 1830-1886 and undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1890 and undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: general, 1860-1899 and undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: from John Early, 1854-1859 (Box 2)
  - Financial papers, 1830-1889 (Box 2)
  - Biographical papers and letters of reference, 1835-1899 and undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1855 and undated (Box 2)
  - Newspapers: James A. Riddick obituary in the Petersburg Daily Index-Appeal, 1899 September 9 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers: Richmond Christian Advocate, 1863-1895 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers: Christian Advocate, 1880 February 28 and 1903 June 25 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers: The Saratoga Sun, 1881 April 30 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers: Daily Post, Petersburg VA, 1878 August 5, 9, 12, 19 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers: The Richmond Dispatch, 1898 July 29 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers: The Church Evangelist, 1858 (Box 3)
  - Newspapers: The Methodist, 1899 September-October (Box 3)